Rose Associates Inc. records 8972723
Avery Architectural and Fine Arts Library
Rose Associates Inc. records
1935-2004
1935-1983
Avery Architectural and Fine Arts Library
Rose, Elihu, 1933-
Rose Associates, Inc
8972723
5 document boxes
1 manuscript box
4 print boxes
Rose Associates, Inc. is a prominent New York real estate development firm. The collection contains construction photographs, brochures, newspaper clippings, advertising materials, and other records related to the construction of apartment complexes overseen by the historic firm between 1920 and 1980. Notable projects within the collection include the Madison Belvedere, Park Gramercy, Georgetown Plaza, and Metropolis.
Publication Date
1935-2004
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series: Corporate Records and Project Records.
General Note
The Rose Associates, Inc. Records were donated to Avery Architectural & Fine Arts Library by Elihu Rose in 2011
Restrictions on Access
This collection is available for use by appointment in the Department of Drawings & Archives, Avery Architectural and Fine Arts Library, Columbia University. For further information and to make an appointment, please email avery-drawings@library.columbia.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source of acquisition--Elihu Rose. Method of acquisition--Donated;; Date of acquisition--2011. Accession number--2011.007.
Related Material
Real Estate Brochure Collection at Avery Architectural & Fine Arts Library
Related Material
Boak & Raad architectural drawings, 1949-1958, Department of Drawings & Archives, Avery Architectural and Fine Arts Library, Columbia University
Biographical / Historical
Rose Associates was founded in the 1920s by brothers Samuel B. and David Rose. The company originally managed properties in the Bronx and has grown to oversee more than 31,000 apartments in New York. This collection focuses mainly on the properties managed by Samuel B. and David Rose, as well as Frederick Phineas Rose and Elihu Rose, between 1920 to 1980. There is also limited information on later projects. Some of the most notable properties included in this collection are the Madison Belvedere, Park Gramercy, and Metropolis.
Scope and Content
The Rose Associates collection consists primarily of construction photographs, brochures, newspaper clippings, and other records of the construction of apartment complexes overseen by Rose Associates. The collection also includes advertising materials from these projects. There is limited information on later projects.
Scope and Content
Series I: Corporate Records/Background Material covers the informational materials of Rose Associates, building fact sheets, and various photographs for their properties from 1990-2000.
Scope and Content
Series II: Project Records is made up of 3 subseries. Subseries 1: General contains construction photographs, floorplans, and advertising materials for apartment complexes in Manhattan, including 4 E. 89th Street, Park Gramercy, and the Sheffield. It also has records for similar projects in the Bronx, notably Schuyler Village. Architects are listed when known, but there are many cases where this information was not available. Subseries 2: Albums includes newspaper and magazine clippings for 1180 Company, Banker's Trust Building, and Walden Terrace. Subseries 3: Ledgers contains records of construction costs for a number of projects including the Keystone Building, 1180 Avenue of the Americas, 280 Park Avenue, and Georgetown Plaza. Several of the ledgers are organized by holding corporation instead of project.
Apartment houses -- New York (State) -- New York; Architects -- New York (State) -- New York; Buildings -- New York (State) -- New York; Real estate management -- New York (State) -- New York; Real estate business -- New York (State) -- New York; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc; Albums (books); Brochures; Ledgers (account books); Photographs; Rose Associates, Inc; Eastmore Realty Corporation; Gramercy Development Corporation; Jackson Development Corporation
- Series I: Corporate Records/Background Material
  - Brochures and Manuals, undated (Box 01, Folder 01 to 04)
    Scope and Contents
    (4 folders)
  - Building Fact Sheets, 1963-1998 (Box 01, Folder 05 to 06)
    (2 folders)
  - Floor Plans Booklet, undated (Box 01, Folder 07)
    Includes floor plans for the following apartments: 60 East 8th Street, 63 East 9th Street, 245 East 40th Street, 300 East 40th Street, 211 East 53rd Street, 322 West 57th Street, 333 West 57th Street, 20 East 68th Street, 240 East 76th Street, 45 East 89th Street, and 7 Lexington Avenue
  - Hannah Leah Rose Settlement, 1955 Nov (Box 09)
    Portfolio of plans
  - Photographs, David and Frederick Rose, undated (Box 01, Folder 08)
    3 items
  - Photographs, Various Properties, undated (Box 09)
    14 items
  - Publication Media Printed Information, 1997 (Box 01, Folder 09)
    Memoranda, Newsletters, Clippings, Maps, and Statistic charts
  - Real Estate Forum, 1960 Nov, 1962 Apr, 1966 Nov (Box 01, Folder 10)
  - Westcroft Realty Corp. (Hartsdale, NY), undated (Box 01, Folder 11)
    Brochure: 2 items
- Series II: Project Records
  - Subseries 1: General
    - 110 West 57th Street (New York, NY), undated (Box 01, Folder 12)
      Architect William I. Hohauser
      Brochure: 1 item
    - 215 East 79th Street (New York, NY), ca. 1960s (Box 01, Folder 13)
      Brochures, Offering Statement, and 1 Photograph
    - 22 Saw Mill River Road (Hawthorne, NY), 1984 (Box 01, Folder 14)
      Matthew J. Warshauer P.C. Architects
    - 45 East 89th Street (New York, NY), 1967-1969 (Box 01, Folder 15 to 18)
      Associate Architects: The Office of Philip Birnbaum and Oppenheimer, Brady and Lehrecke
      Photographs: 143 items (4 folders)
    - 45 East 89th Street (New York, NY), 1969, undated (Box 01, Folder 19)
      Brochures and Flyers requesting tenant participation in a survey
    - 45 East 89th Street (New York, NY), undated (Box 01, Folder 20)
      Floor plans
    - 45 East 89th Street (New York, NY), 1977 (Box 01, Folder 21)
      Thank you notes, children's drawings, and 16 photographs of kindergarten class who temporarily occupied 45 East 89th Street during the gas shortage.
    - 99-61 67th Road (Forest Hills, Queens, NY), 1946-1947 (Box 01, Folder 22)
      Photographs: 41 items
    - Allegro, 62 West 62nd Street (New York, NY), undated (Box 01, Folder 23)
    - Andrew Jackson, 35-20 Leverich Street (Jackson Heights, Queens, NY), undated (Box 01, Folder 24)
    - Banker's Trust Building, 280 Park Avenue (New York, NY), 1960-1962 (Box 01, Folder 25)
      Photographs: 77 items
    - Boswell, 84-10 37th Avenue (Jackson Heights, Queens, NY), 1952 (Box 01, Folder 26)
      Photograph: 1 item
    - Branford House, Westchester, Croes, Noble and Gleasons Avenues (Bronx, NY), 1962 (Box 01, Folder 27)
      Brown & Guenther, Architects
      1 Bound Report, "A Limited Profit Housing Project Supervised by the Housing and Redevelopment Board of the City of New York"
    - The Broakford, 65 Park Terrace West (New York, NY), undated (Box 02, Folder 01)
      Leo Stillman, Architect
      Floor Plans
    - The Churchill, 300 West 40th Street (New York, NY), 1965-1967, undated (Box 02, Folder 02 to 03)
      20 Photographs, 1 Negative, Brochures, and Floor Plans (2 folders)
    - Colonnade 57, 347 West 57th Street (New York, NY), 1982, undated (Box 02, Folder 04)
      Brochures, Promotional Material, First Annual Meeting of the Unit Owners (1982 Nov 23)
    - Eastmore House, 240 East 76th Street (New York, NY), undated (Box 02, Folder 05)
      Leo Stillman, Architect; Boak & Raad, Associate Architects
      1 Photograph, Brochures, and Floor Plans
    - Evergreen Gardens, 950-955 Evergreen Avenue (Bronx, NY), 1961-1963 (Box 02, Folder 06)
      Architect: Pomerance & Breines
      86 Photographs, Brochure, and Promotional Material
    - Executive House, 45 East Hartsdale Avenue (Hartsdale, NY), undated (Box 02, Folder 07)
      Brochure
    - Fenimore House, 199 East Hartsdale Avenue (Hartsdale, NY), undated (Box 02, Folder 08)
      Brochure and Floor Plan
    - Garth Manor, 281 Garth Road (Scarsdale, NY), undated (Box 02, Folder 09)
      Brochures and Floor Plans
    - Georgetown Plaza, 60 East 8th Street (New York, NY), 1965-1967, undated (Box 02, Folder 10)
      41 Photographs, Brochures, and Floor Plans
    - Goodhue House, 20 East 35th Street (New York, NY), undated (Box 02, Folder 11)
      William M. Dowling, Architects
    - Hartridge House, 111 East Hartsdale Avenue (Hartsdale, NY), undated (Box 02, Folder 12)
    - Hawthorne, 211 East 53rd Street (New York, NY), undated (Box 02, Folder 13)
      Architects: Boak and Raad
      4 Photographs, Brochures, Promotional Material, And Floor Plan
    - Heathcote Court, 85 Wiltshire Road (Scarsdale, NY), undated (Box 02, Folder 14)
      Floor Plan
    - Homestead, 80 East Hartsdale Avenue (Scarsdale, NY), undated (Box 02, Folder 15)
    - Kingsbridge Gardens, 234th Street and Kingsbridge Ave., Corlear Ave., and Broadway (Bronx, NY), 1962-1966 (Box 02, Folder 16 to 18)
      Pomerance & Breines
      1 Bound Report, "A Limited Profit Housing Project Supervised by the Housing and Redevelopment Board of the City of New York", Papers, Floor Plans, and 113 Photographs (3 folders)
    - Leyland House, 945 Underhill Avenue (Bronx, NY), 1960s, 2001 (Box 02, Folder 19)
      Brochures, Promotional Material, Clippings, Specifications, Floor Plans and Offering Summary (2001_
    - Madison Belvedere, 10 East 29th Street (New York, NY), 1990s (Box 02, Folder 20)
      Brochures and Clippings
    - Madison Green, 5 East 22nd Street (New York, NY), 1981-1983 (Box 02, Folder 21 to 24)
      Photographs: 224 items (4 photographs)
    - Madison Green, 5 East 22nd Street (New York, NY), undated (Box 02, Folder 25 to 26)
      Architect: Philip Birnbaum, P.C.
      Brochures and Floor Plans (2 folders)
    - Marlborough House, 245 East 40th Street (New York, NY), 1969, 1970s (Box 02, Folder 27 to 28)
      Brochures, Floor Plan, Papers, and 149 Photographs (2 folders)
    - Metropolis, 150 East 44th Street (New York, NY), 1980s, 2000s (Box 03, Folder 01)
    - Nathan Hale Gardens, 3411 Irwin Avenue (Bronx, NY), 1962, undated (Box 03, Folder 02 to 03)
      Floor Plan and 144 Photographs (2 folder)
    - Oakwood, 99-21 67th Road (Forest Hill, Queens, NY), undated (Box 03, Folder 04)
      Floor Plans and 1 Negative
    - Olmstead House, 69-01 35th Avenue (Jackson Heights, Queens, NY), undated (Box 03, Folder 05)
      Architects: Samuel Paul & Seymour Jarmul
      Brochures and 19 Photographs
    - Parc Vista, 801 15th Street South (Arlington, VA), 1990s (Box 03, Folder 06 to 08)
      Floor Plans, Promotional Material, Memorandum and other papers, 2 Disk Drives, 4 Photographs, 4 Transparencies (3 folders)
    - The Park Gramercy, 7-9 Lexington Avenue (New York, NY), 1950s (Box 03, Folder 09)
      Architect: Boak & Raad
      Brochures, Floor Plan, Clipping, 3 Photographs, 1 Blueprint of Dental Suite for Drs. W.D. Berg & C. Blackarsh (1951)
    - Park Terrace Gardens, Park Terrace West (New York, NY), 1970s (Box 03, Folder 10)
      Albert Goldhammer, Architect
      Brochures, Documents, Floor Plans, 1 Photograph
    - Randall House, 63 East 9th Street (New York, NY), 1950s (Box 03, Folder 11 to 12)
      Boak & Raad, Architects
      Brochures, Floor Plans, Press Release, and 19 Photographs (2 folders)
    - Rockwood, 20 East 68th Street (New York, NY), 1954-1965 (Box 03, Folder 13)
      Brochures, Promotional Material, Correspondence, Floor Plans, 2 Photograph and 1 Negative
    - Scarborough Manor (Briarcliff Manor, NY), undated (Box 03, Folder 14)
    - Schuyler House, 1220 Croes Avenue (Bronx, NY), 1960s (Box 03, Folder 15)
      Brochures, Floor Plans, Clippings
    - Sheffield, 322 West 57th Street (New York, NY), 1978-1979, 2001-2004 (Box 03, Folder 16 to 17)
      Brochures, Clippings, 2 Bound Portfolios, and 51 Photographs (2 folders)
    - Spruceridge House, 241-245 East 25th Street (New York, NY), 1964 (Box 03, Folder 18)
      Floor Plans and Project Analysis
    - Stewart Heights, 25 and 35 Stewart Place (Mount Kisco, NY), undated (Box 03, Folder 19)
      Architect: Lawrence Rothman Assoc.
      Brochures, Newspaper Clippings
    - Tower 53, 159 West 53rd Street (New York, NY), undated (Box 03, Folder 20)
      Brochures, Floor Plans
    - Tower 58, 58 West 58th Street (New York, NY), undated (Box 03, Folder 21)
    - Walden Terrace, 64th Avenue at 98th Street (Forest Hills, Queens, NY), undated (Box 04, Folder 01)
      Brochures, Plans, Clippings, 22 Photographs
    - Westmore, 333 West 57th Street (New York, NY), 1974-1986 (Box 04, Folder 02)
      Brochures, Floor Plans, Plans, Job Orders, Photograph
    - Whitebrook, 325 Main Street (White Plains, NY), undated (Box 04, Folder 03)
      Photographs: 14 items
    - Wingate, 201 East 37th Street (New York, NY), 1960, undated (Box 04, Folder 04 to 05)
      Construction Records and Floor plans (2 folders)
    - Winthrop Gardens, 2440 Olinville Avenue (Bronx, NY), undated (Box 04, Folder 06)
  - Subseries 2: Albums
    - Loose Material from Unidentified Album, 1961-1965 (Box 04, Folder 07)
    - Banker's Trust, 1960 Oct to 1961 Nov (Box 06, Folder 01 to 25)
      Magazine Clippings, Newspaper Clippings, and Radio TV Reports (25 Folders)
    - 1180 Company, 1961 Sep to 1962 Nov (Box 07, Folder 01 to 11)
      Magazine Clippings and Newspaper Clippings (11 folders)
    - Walden Terrace, 1948 Jan to 1949 Apr (Box 07, Folder 12 to 30)
      Newspaper Clippings (19 folders)
    - Advertising - Mitchell Lama, 1962 Sep - 1965 Feb (Box 08, Folder 01 to 31)
      Magazine Clippings and Newspaper Clippings, Comparative Analysis Pre-War Apartments, Documents, Housing Permit 334-346 West 59th Street, Photographs, Real Estate Conference (1948 Apr 22) (31 folders)
    - Ezra Stoller Associates Portfolio, undated (Box 09)
      Photographs of properties including 1 Battery Park Plaza. Keystone Building,
  - Subseries 3: Ledgers
    - 1000 Grand Concourse (Bronx, NY), 1935-1936 (Box 05)
      Construction Records
    - 280 Park Avenue (New York, NY), 1961-1964 (Box 05)
    - 331-45 West 57th Street, 334-46 West 58th Street (New York, NY), 1940-1941 (Box 05)
      Construction Corporation: 57th Street Construction Corp.; Construction Records
    - 58 West 58th Street, 45 East 89th Street, Seamen's Bank, undated (Box 05)
      Construction Records, Contract Records
    - 84-10 34th Avenue (Flushing, Queens, NY), 1950-1951 (Box 05)
      Construction Corporation: Jackson Dev. Corp., Stonewall Development Corp., Fenton Holding Corp.; Construction Records
    - Barnes, 1933 (Box 05)
    - Eastmore House, 240 East 76th Street (New York, NY), 1955-1956 (Box 05)
      Construction Corporation: Eastmore Reality Corp.; Construction Records
    - Evergreen, Nathan Hale, Kingsbridge, 1961-1962 (Box 05)
    - The Homestead, Georgetown Plaza, The Churchill, undated (Box 05)
    - Jackson Manor, 35-20 Leverich Street (Jackson Heights, Queens, NY), Olmstead House, 69-01 35th Avenue (Jackson Heights, Queens, NY), Hall Manor Tower (New York, NY), 1961 (Box 05)
    - Keystone Building, 99 High Street (Boston, MA) and Bankers Trust Company, 1180 Avenue of the Americas (New York, NY), 1964-1969 (Box 05)
    - Leland House, Branford House, Winthrop Gardens, undated (Box 05)
    - Marlborough House, undated (Box 05)
    - The Park Gramercy, 7-9 Lexington Avenue (New York, NY), 1950-1951 (Box 05)
      Construction Corporation: Gramercy Development Corp.; Construction Records
    - Park Terrace Gardens, 70 Park Terrace West (New York, NY), 1939-1940 (Box 05)
    - Repar Realty Corp., Rockwood Realty Corp., 1954-1955 (Box 05)
    - Thornley Realty Corp. and Rostin Realty Corp., 1946-1947 (Box 05)
    - Tryon Gardens, Inc., 1937-1938 (Box 05)
    - Untitled Ledger (Bronx, NY), 1929 (Box 05)
    - Walden Terrace, 64th Avenue at 98th Street (Forest Hills, Queens, NY), 1948-1949 (Box 05)
      Construction Corporation: Nipark Realty Corp.; Construction Records
    - Wentworth, 331-45 West 57th Street and 334-46 West 58th Streets (New York, NY), 1932 (Box 05)
      Construction Corporation: Academy Home Planners; Construction Records